Today's דף *daf* is קמ"ב *Kuf Mem Beis*, 142. We pick up
at the bottom of קמ"א *Kuf Mem Aleph* on עמוד ב' *Amud
Bais*. We're dealing with the משנה mishna, *Mishna* that gives some scenarios
about a man who says if my wife gives birth to a
male child let him get a hundred dollars, to female child two
hundred, etc. and then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is dealing with the
implications that spin off of this. One issue was the question about
what if the child was a טומטום *tumtum* and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* had an interesting discussion about whether טומטום *tumtum* is בריה בפני
עצמו *biryah bifnei atzmo* and doesn't fall into either category and gets
nothing, which as we mentioned at the top was interesting in terms
of the whole issue of what do you call it of like
you know the gender binary. Then the other possibility is that it's
a ספק safek *safek*. One possibility, I don't know if Dan explored
it with you yesterday, is that even if it is a ספק
*safek*, the person is a ספק *safek* in terms of their identity,
maybe still right there was one position of אביי Abaye *Abaye* of
וייתי ולא יהבינן ליה *v'yeiti v'lo yahavinan lei* that he doesn't get
either as a boy or as a girl in terms of the
ירושה yerusha *yerusha*. One way to understand that is a בריה *biryah*,
but another way to understand that is and he doesn't even get
the you know the common denominator of the two, and one way
to understand that might have to do with how you know about
what a person's intent is when they say boy or girl. They
might intend somebody that is obviously in one category as opposed to
somebody who is you know might objectively be a boy or girl
but it's not clearly be identified. So those were some issues that
came up around the issue about what do you call it about
טומטום *tumtum*. Also, I would be remiss if I did not, I
don't know if Dan did it, but you know the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* also asked like why you know why is the guy giving
more money to his daughter than his son? There's a general obviously
bias towards you know men towards boys and sons, etc. So one
answer was, well, everybody wants a daughter to be the oldest child
because then she'll help out in raising the kids. My wife who
was the first of eight can readily attest to testify to that
one. But also, but you know in the context of that discussion,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says oh but is you know it had
an issue about the joke. Oh you said the joke so I
don't have to repeat the joke, so Michael already told the joke.
So I knew you were getting at that. That's totally what I
was getting at. Okay, anyway, getting to a discussion are boys better
than girls? One rabbi said I prefer girls, so why did he
prefer girls? So maybe he had only daughters and so no actually
he had a lot of sons. But the joke says the reason
he preferred girls, oh thank you, was because his sons-in-law were bigger
תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* than his sons. So now everybody attest. Anyway,
and the last thing I'll just say although Michael said before I
can't resist, you know in the middle of that discussion the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says you know, well, you know it says God blessed
אברהם *Avraham* with everything בכל *bakol* and so it said he had
a daughter her name was בכל *Bakol*, doesn't that show daughters are
better?
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says one minute if אברהם *Avraham* had a
daughter by the name of בכל *Bakol*, why did he have to
go to all this trouble to marry off יצחק *Yitzchak*, right? If
since a בן נח *ben Noach* is allowed to marry his half-sister
on his father's side, so why didn't יצחק *Yitzchak* just marry off
his half-sister בכל *Bakol*? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* so you know anyway
that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*'s question. So the answer, so whatever תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* gives the answer he gives, but anyway but the other answer
that they give is well יצחק *Yitzchak* wanted to marry a real
woman not a מדרש *Midrash*. So anyway, okay but I hear that
Michael already told over the joke yesterday. You mentioned it too. In
my name, in my name. Anyway, I was the one who came
up with it. I'm good at retelling jokes. Okay anyway,
so anyway, but back to where we are. The real question now
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has been focused on at the end
of yesterday and is going to focus on today is the question
about I don't understand how this works all together. If he is
trying to get his unborn son or daughter to own this gift
right, you know, and he's trying to transfer it to them right
now to this to this unborn fetus, how does that work? Don't
we say that a person can't be you know המזכה לעובר לא
קנה kanah. *hamazakeh l'ubar lo kana*? If somebody tries to transfer ownership
to a fetus even through a third party even it's זכין לאדם
שלא בפניו *zachin l'adam shelo b'fanav* that doesn't work cause the fetus
doesn't exist yet, which I was raised as like fascinating questions right
about the whole all those abortion questions and how much is you
know considered to be a life and an independent life and so
on. So those you know they do get brought into those other
types of discussion. Anyway, so that's the position of המזכה לעובר לא
קנה *hamazakeh l'ubar lo kana* is רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*
and therefore when רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna*
was what מחלוקת *machlokes*?
Well right, but but רב הונא Rav Huna. *Rav Huna* but anyway
but רב הונא *Rav Huna* and therefore רב הונא *Rav Huna* says
I don't know who the author of the משנה mishna, *Mishna* is
because I don't know of any position that would say that you
can transfer ownership to a fetus and even though the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says maybe if it fits in with רב מאיר *Rav Meir*
דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם adam makneh davar she-lo ba
la-olam, *d'amar adam makneh davar shelo ba l'olam*, no that's different because
there at least the recipient is בעולם ba-olam, *ba'olam*, maybe it fits
in with the idea that what do you call it
that oh what about the fact that sometimes a fetus can inherit
and we have evidence that a fetus can inherit? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says well that's a natural inheritance that happens by itself
but to treat him as an active entity that he
could
take
possession. Okay, so now let's continue with the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
three lines
up, did we do the מבשרני *mivasereni*?
Yeah, three lines from the bottom. ולימא ליה בשיולדה *v'leima lei b'sheyalda*.
Wait a minute, why doesn't רב הונא *Rav Huna* say I can
explain the משנה mishna *Mishna* that he didn't say "I am transferring
if my wife gives birth in the future to a male, I
am gifting him a hundred dollars now"? Let's say he's somewhere in
a distant place and he doesn't know what and his wife already
gave birth and he says "if my wife gave birth to a
male, I am מזכה mazkeh *mezakeh* him a hundred dollars. If she
gave birth to a female, I'm transferring to the, to her as
a baby, two hundred dollars." So let's say the transfer's occurring to
actually the child that's already been born, he just doesn't know its
sex, he's not around. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי
דקתני סיפא *ei hachi diktani seifa*, one minute, but then it wouldn't
work with the end of the משנה mishnah *Mishna*, because the end
of the משנה mishnah *Mishna* says ואם אמר כל מה שתלד אשתי
יטול *v'im amar kol mah sheteiled ishti yitol*, if he says "whomever
my wife gives birth to, let them take, you know, a hundred
dollars," and that gets into the whole בירור *beirur* discussion, but our
point is that it's in the, the verb is in the future.
הרי זה יטול *harei zeh yitol*, so he can take it, even
in a case of a טומטום *tumtum*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, so it should, כל שתלד *kol sheteiled*, it shouldn't say "whomever
my wife gives birth to, will give birth to," כל שילדה מיבעי
ליה *kol sheyalda mibayei leh*, whomever she did give birth to. So
that's not a good way of explaining the משנה mishnah *Mishna*. Okay,
so he says I can't explain the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* because the,
it seems to be that the kid is still a עובר ubar
*ubar* and taking possession, and I believe that nobody holds of the
position that מזכה לעובר קנה mezakeh le'ubar kanah, *mezakeh l'ubar kanah*. So
top of דף קמ"ב עמוד א' *daf kuf mem bet amud aleph*,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולימא ליה דאמר לכשתלד *v'leima lei
d'amar liksheteiled*, how about this? I'm going to try to transfer to
the עובר ubar *ubar*, but not now while the kid is still
a עובר ubar *ubar*. I will try to transfer it so that
at the moment the עובר uber, *ubar* is born, he or she
will take possession of it. So the act of קנין kinyan *kinyan*
is done now to take effect for that person once they're בא
לעולם *ba l'olam*. That's an interesting mechanism, right? If Michael here is
being קונה koneh? *koneh* for the עובר uber *ubar*, I say "give
me your handkerchief and you be קונה koneh, *koneh* a hundred dollars
for this unborn עובר uber *ubar*." So you could say he can't
represent the עובר uber *ubar*, the עובר uber *ubar* is not seen
as a person yet as a legal person, not even as a
minor, right? It's seen as like it doesn't exist so you can't
represent him. But can you do an act that should that right
now you can't represent that person but you can do it on
behalf of somebody who and it will take effect when they are
a person who can be represented? So you could understand why that
might be a little difficult, since the act right now has to
be seen as an act of that person who's taking possession. Right?
If it was Michael is doing an act of taking possession and
saying "that object that I'm taking possession of from דוב *Dov* should
be owned by this עובר uber *ubar* when it's born," maybe that
works. At least you have an act to get started with. But
if his whole, the only act works by him representing the עובר
uber *ubar*, you know, maybe it does work, maybe it doesn't work.
Okay, so that's the question: can it work even if you can't
be מזכה לעובר mezakke l'ubar, *mezakeh l'ubar*? Can you be מזכה לעובר
mezakke l'ubar. *mezakeh l'ubar* that it should take effect not now but
when the עובר uber *ubar* is born? Okay, can't say עובר uber
*ubar* anymore, we have to say לכשתלד *liksheteiled* or something.
Yeah, so if I wanted to, would it be the same thing?
I just use the words "into this world," if I'm מקדיש *makdish*
the עובר uber *ubar* in a cow to as a קרבן *korban*,
I said nothing then, right?
Shouldn't it be the same thing?
Yeah, so that gets into didn't the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discuss that
already or is that coming up? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to bring in that whole discussion about מקדיש *makdish*, so hold off.
Okay? It didn't have that yesterday? I'm getting confused, the two דפים
*dapim* are running together.
Yeah, wasn't it yesterday if it's a male versus if it's a
female and then if it comes out,
yeah, where was it? Or something or twins, then neither is...
No, I'm talking about being מקדיש *makdish*.
All right, I think the מקדיש *makdish* is coming up if it
didn't already come up. Okay, let's hold off on that. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, ולימא ליה דאמר לכשתלד *v'leima lei
d'amar liksheteiled*. רב הונא לטעמיה *Rav Huna l'taameih*, רב הונא *Rav Huna*
goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רב הונא אף לכשתלד לא קנה
af lechishe'taled lo kanah. *d'amar Rav Huna af liksheteiled lo kanah*. רב
הונא *Rav Huna* is of the belief that it wouldn't make a
difference. So therefore when רב הונא *Rav Huna* is saying he doesn't
think like if the עובר uber *ubar* doesn't exist yet then how
can somebody represent the עובר uber *ubar* even לכשתלד *liksheteiled* once the
עובר uber *ubar* is born?
Reason is because it's like in the belly?
I mean like it doesn't, it doesn't have it's not a legal
entity yet. Okay, so I mean even, you know, so therefore right
maybe it has to do with עובר ubar ירך אמו *ubar yerech
imo*, it's just seen as a part of the mother, it's not
its own legal entity. Okay, so therefore he says that it does
not work. So therefore when רב הונא *Rav Huna* is saying "I
don't know who said our משנה Mishnah *Mishna*," what he's really saying
is that I mean it's ironic because he could have framed it
the other way, right? He could have said like "this משנה Mishnah
*Mishna* is a contradiction to רב הונא *Rav Huna*'s claim that you
can't transfer ownership to a עובר ubar. *ubar*" because you see that
you can. But רב הונא *Rav Huna*, you know, the good defense
the best defense is a good offense, so רב הונא *Rav Huna*
starts with saying "this משנה mishna, *Mishna* can't go like anybody" because
you know, but it's all based on his assumption that א: מזכה
לעובר לא קנה mezakke l'ubar lo kana. *aleph: mezakeh l'ubar lo kanah*
and ב: *bet* that it wouldn't even work even לכשתלד *liksheteiled*, even
if you say it should take effect when the child is born.
Now he says, אמר רב נחמן, Rav Nachman says רב נחמן Rav
Nachman says המזכה לעובר לא קנה לכשתלד קנה. hamizakeh le'ubar lo kanah
lechishe'taled kanah. רב נחמן Rav Nachman actually says no, an עובר can't
take possession now, but you can do the act for the עובר
to take possession once the עובר is born and becomes a, you
know, and becomes a child, a baby, an infant. ורב הונא אמר,
v'Rav Huna amar, אף לכשתלד לא קנה. It doesn't even work when
once he's born. So right now what we've seen is that it's
really a way of saying that רב הונא's position doesn't fit with
the משנה, although רב הונא is saying that as a critique or
as a question on the משנה, but that רב נחמן can say
that the actual משנה makes sense. You can't transfer ownership to a
fetus while it's a fetus, but you can do an act for
the fetus to take effect once the fetus is born. And now
we get a position that's even more, like, lenient or expansive. רב
ששת אמר, Rav Sheshet amar, אחד זה ואחד זה קנה. echad zeh
ve-echad zeh kanah. Actually, I disagree even with the principle we started
with. Even, you can even transfer ownership to a fetus even while
a fetus is still a fetus, whether before, while, whether to take
effect after it's born or while it's still a fetus, either way
it works. Rejects רב הונא. ורב ששת, v'Rav Sheshet, the גמרא Gemara
says like
this, אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, מנא אמינא לה? mena amina
lah? Where do I get this idea from? Okay,
by the way, you know, the גמרא Gemara earlier compared it to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir about אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, makneh
davar she-lo ba la-olam, right? But you know, and the גמרא sort
of said even if you're מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, this is
worse because the fetus isn't even yet the other party. But you
can see that you can go the opposite direction, right? You could
say, you could say that if I try to transfer fruit on
a tree to Michael and the fruit isn't even, you know, not
the tree that bores fruit, just the fruit, and the fruit hasn't
even, you know, come out yet, that's really like what did I
sell him? There's no object here that I'm selling him. So right
now, even today we talk about selling a future in the object.
We don't talk about selling the object, right? Whereas a fetus, if
the woman's al- at least if the woman is already pregnant, right?
Then you could understand that the fetus is a, you know, is
already like partially בעולם, and you know, you see some, so you
know, you could imagine that that could work at least as good
as some cases of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, maybe even better. So
רב ששת's Rav Sheshet position that מזכה לעובר קנה, mezake le'ubar kana
especially if the woman's already pregnant, is a pretty reasonable position, okay,
certainly within the world of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and maybe even
more than that. So let's see what רב ששת Rav Sheshet says.
ורב ששת אמר, v'Rav Sheshet amar, אחד זה ואחד זה קנה. echad
zeh ve-echad zeh kanah. Either way it takes
effect. אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, מנא אמינא לה? mena amina
lah? Where do I know this from? דתניא, detanya, גר שמת, ger
she-met, ובזבזו ישראל נכסיו. u-vizbezu Yisrael nechasav. Yeah, you know, I gotta
tell you, if there's a גר, ger, what?
You say- someone's looted, it's like- Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. I gotta tell you, if you're a גר, ger, you want
to be writing a will really, really carefully because I can just
imagine all of the vultures hovering around waiting for this גר ger
to die so that the property is ownerless so that they can
descend on the property and take possession of it, if he doesn't
have any children after he had converted. So that's what happened. He
didn't have any children after he converted, he dies, and everybody essentially
looted, I mean, the verb is a powerful verb, like looted his
property. Great, he's dead, free for all, let's grab his
property. ושמעו, she-shamu,
שיש לו בן. she-yesh lo ben. Presumably after they did this, they
heard that he actually, wait, I heard he actually has a biological
son that he gave birth to after he converted. או שהיתה אשתו
מעוברת, o she-hayetah ishto me'uberet, or his wife, because his wife wouldn't
inherit him, right? That would be also the irony, that even if
he was married, right? A wife doesn't inherit her husband, even if
there are no heirs, even in the case of a גר. ger.
So the only way that even if he's married that he'll pass
on his property is if his wife gives birth, or if his
wife was pregnant. Okay? And if she would give birth to a
viable child, the property would go to that child. Okay? So after
they looted his property, they realized wait, he's got an heir, or
he's possibly got an heir, you know, once his wife gives birth.
חייבים להחזיר. chayavim lehachzir.
So then they have to put all the money back, every- you
know, take back the TV and the whatever and the computer and
the- you know, the car, put it all back on the estate,
okay? Let's wait till the son shows up or till the fetus
is born. החזירו הכל, hechziru hakol, they restored it all, ואחר כך,
ve-achar kach, שמעו, she-shamu, שמת בנו, she-met beno, או שהפילה אשתו. o
she-hipilah ishto. And then they heard actually what happened was was that
the son died, okay, or that the- now presumably that means after
you looted the property. So the order was... Okay, right, here's the
גר, ger, he dies. Okay, here's his property, okay, whatever, we'll make
it, I don't know what we'll make it. Okay, anyway, whatever it
is, here's his property. So they go and they grab his property,
okay, and then here, the גר's ger got a son, okay, and
then they hear that he's
got a son, okay, I don't know what we'll do, they hear
he has a son, okay, so then they, so then they return
the prop- well actually here, so then he I guess he takes
the property, then he returns the property, and then here, the son
dies, okay, or the wife miscarries, okay. So in that case when
he took the property... Then the son dies, now there's no surviving
heir, now it's a new free-for-all, right? So then it says, חייבין
הלה שהחזיר קרקע וחזר והחזיק בשנייה, Chayyavin haleh shehechazir karka vechazar vehechezik
basheniyah, if he took
re-possession of it, קנה.
Now he'll pay, now he'll own it. ובראשונה לא קנה, Uvarishonah lo
kanah, but this wasn't good because in this case he still had
a son, okay? So in this case he still had a son,
this taking of possession would not work. But the case is not
only that he's got a son, okay, that's one scenario, I'm drawing
him small because he's a son, okay, but the other scenario is
that his wife is pregnant, okay? You like my pictures? Okay, so
anyway, so his wife is pregnant, okay, so that's the case. So
the point is and then he returned it and then his wife
miscarried, okay? Well, I guess we'll leave that, that picture, but anyway
either way it's sad. Anyway, so the question is if, if he
says you see that the fetus was קונה? koneh, Because if the
fetus wasn't קונה, koneh. then why is only the second חזקה chazakah
good after the wife miscarries, right? Meaning the first חזקה chazakah maybe
wasn't good before the fetus was born or had been miscarried because
if it turns out that the fetus is born and is viable,
then the גר ger had an heir and obviously, you know, it's
an interesting question because if you say that a fetus doesn't inherit,
so who owned the property in the interim? Right? The גר ger
died, the fetus didn't inherit, then for the, then three months later
the fetus is born, then the fetus inherits. Who owned it in
the interim? But okay, some abstract entity of the estate in limbo.
But it still would be clear that you couldn't take possession in
that interim if there's going to be a born child who's going
to inherit. Okay, so that's what, but so if, but if the
child, if she miscarried and the child was never born and the
fetus didn't inherit initially because the fetus can't take possession of property,
so then why did that first act of taking possession not work?
Since in the end there was no heir, that first act should
have worked. So that's what the גמרא says. Doesn't it even on
the first part? In other words even if מעוברת, me'uberet, why if,
if? Well, that's what I'm saying. Somehow we assume, I mean why
do you have to give it back? So that's what I'm saying.
Somehow we're going to assume and we're not going to take it
for granted that even if an עובר, a fetus, can't be קונה,
koneh once he's born he did inherit his father, right? And somehow,
I mean again is it retroactively, is it only מכאן ולהבא? mikan
ule-haba? What happens to the estate? But it's not free for other
people to take, okay? Because it's sort of, you have to just,
again, the גמרא doesn't explain why, but you understand the logic. There's
going to be an heir. This estate is being held for that
future heir. Okay, so that we're taking for granted. And this would
be, you know, the גר ger as a שכיב מרע shchiv mera
theoretically could have gifted it all to his wife and none of
this then would be applicable, right? Yeah, we just said it's, well,
yeah, it's an interesting if they would have a גר ger do
a שכיב מרע shchiv mera because a גר ger doesn't have, isn't
a בר מוריש, bar morish, he can't be מוריש, morish, but he
certainly could have gifted as a normal מתנת ברי. matnas bari. Okay.
So yeah, this is where the guy took it number two. We'll
see about that about a גר ger being a שכיב מרע. shchiv
mera. Alright. So anyway, so the גמרא says like this. So it's
only the second guy. So he says, ואי סלקא דעתך עובר לא
קנה. ve'isalkadatch uber lo kanah. Now if the עובר wasn't קונה. koneh
So again, if the עובר was born eventually viable, of course it
would go to the heir. But in the end the עובר was
miscarried and if he wasn't, didn't own it at the time when
he was a fetus, למה ליה לאחזוקי בשנייה? lama lei lachzokei basheniyah?
Why did he have to re-take possession? אחזוקי בחדא זימנא. achzokei bechada
zimna. The first taking of possession, the kid was a fetus, the
fetus was never born as a viable heir, so that first taking
of possession should suffice. So it's a good question. So it shows
you that a fetus can take possession. So of course we proved
yesterday that a fetus can inherit. This isn't such a big חידוש,
chiddush, right? Which the obvious answer is, fine, nobody's debating whether a
fetus can inherit. What we're debating is is about whether you can
actively be קונה koneh for a fetus, whether the fetus can sort
of be seen as taking active possession. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
so אביי Abaye gives the easy answer. I mean whatever, the answer
we gave yesterday. ירושה מאליה שאני. yerushah me-eleih shani. Okay fine, a
fetus can take possession, that's not relevant for our discussion. I mean
can inherit. רבא אמר, Rava amar, now רבא Rava says, שאני התם
דריפוי מרפיא בידיה מעיקרא. shani hasam derafui mirafya biyadei me-ikara. There it's,
as רבא Rava says, there, רבא Rava says, you know what, maybe
even a fetus can't inherit. So if a fetus can't inherit, why
did this not work? So he says the reason this didn't work,
if a fetus can't inherit and then it turned out the fetus
died, there was no heir etc., was because even at the moment
when he took possession it was weak in his hand. That's what
the phrase means. Why was it weak in his hand at the
moment he took possession? Because now the funny thing is before it
sounded like, right, I put my bubble here, here, which is like
wife is pregnant after he took possession. and he heard that the
wife was pregnant. So then he's got to return it, right? That
was the case. Right, oh, whoops, didn't mean to do that, put
it all back. Okay, but what רבא Rava seems to be saying,
the רשב״ם Rashbam doesn't say this explicitly but it's hard to imagine
otherwise is even when he took possession he had already heard that
the wife was pregnant. If that were true why would that matter?
Because then he all along the חזקה chazaka is not a meaningful
act of taking possession. He knows that if the wife gives birth
to a viable child, right, or he knows if this reports that
there's a son alive in מדינת הים Medinat Hayam turn out true
he'll have to give it back. So if even at the moment
he took possession he had heard rumors that the wife was pregnant
or there was a son in מדינת הים Medinat Hayam then in
that case he says even though it's true that the עובר was
קונה koneh. the whatever the he could in theory have taken possession
because the עובר didn't inherit a fetus didn't inherit so the point
was was that this really is הפקר hefker at this moment. But
because he knows that he'll have to give it back if the
fetus is born as a viable child he never has like you
know or he might claim he's got real intent to take possession
but it's not real intent because at the back of his mind
he knows that there's a good chance he'll have to give it
back. The הפקר hefker is weakened by that and the and the
קנין kinyan is weakened? The הפקר hefker isn't weakened? Yes because a
because look the this is a kind of a ספק like you
don't know if that עובר is going to be born as a
viable or not. So right. She could she could miscarry, right, or
like מדינת הים Medinat Hayam like he could drown it never comes
you wouldn't know. So it's that's the רפיון. rifyon. That's the weakening.
And like theoretically he could be קונה koneh. because the עובר might
not be but but not really. Sort of like in limbo. That's
where I understand it. I understand but we're going to see in
a minute that it really does seem that it's basically based on
the subjective his subjective reality so hold on. So אביי Abaye says
the עובר was קונה. koneh That the עובר can be יורש yoresh
he just maybe can't be מזכה mezakke but he can be יורש.
yoresh. רבא Rava says the עובר wasn't קונה. koneh So if the
עובר wasn't קונה koneh why couldn't he have just taken possession? And
the answer was even though it really was הפקר hefker and in
the end the עובר never inherited it so it turned out that
it remained הפקר hefker and so on but he but if he
knew and again it's not clear that he did know. Maybe he's
supposed to suspect the possibility of. The גמרא sounds like he heard
afterwards. So either you have to say he heard before or you
have to say he has to suspect the possibility that there might
be an heir somewhere. And since he has to know since he
knows or he has to suspect that possibility even though it really
was הפקר hefker his דעת da'at was not complete even if he
claims his דעת da'at was complete we're going to say his דעת
da'at was not complete and it's not a full taking of possession.
So that could be how it doesn't work. Now Joe wants to
say that maybe it's also some objective reality that it's not fully
הפקר hefker because you know who knows the son the fetus might
be born. Let's see what the גמרא says the נפקא מינה nafka
mina of those two answers are. So the גמרא says מאי בינייהו
mai beinaihu what's the difference between אביי Abaye and רבא? Rava? אביי
says the fetus actually owns it. רבא Rava says the fetus doesn't
own it but your קנין kinyan isn't good because because you're at
the back of your mind you're uncertain whether you're going to be
able to keep it. So the גמרא says what's the difference? איכא
בינייהו דשמע בו שמת ולא מת ואחר כך מת. ika beinaihu deshama
bo shemet velo met ve'achar kach met. He had heard that the
kid had died in fact he had not died but then afterwards
he died. So meaning the נפקא מינה nafka mina is when it's
a different subjective reality that basically so maybe here you heard already
that the wife was pregnant and that made you or you should
have suspected that there might be an heir out there and the
wife was pregnant. So that's what we said made you uncertain in
your act of חזקה. chazaka. But at the same time you heard
that
the wife was pregnant you heard wife miscarried. Okay? So right now
you heard that the wife miscarried while you're taking possession. Alright? Is
there any רפיון rifyon in your subjective mindset? No. Okay? Objectively this
property might still go to the fetus if the fetus is born
viable. But subjectively you actually have heard concrete information that tells you
not only you're assuming there are no heirs hey the kid died
let's grab it if there happens to be any heirs we'll give
it back. Who's going to let's not spend our time researching if
there are heirs then Michael's going to grab it before me. I'm
just going to go grab it if it turns out there'll be
heirs I'll give it back. So there you could say מרפא בידיה
mrapeh beyadei I know there's some possibility. But in this case before
I grabbed it I heard that the heir had already died and
that the wife had miscarried. So I am a hundred percent certain
in my mind that I am going to be able to keep
it. You're wrong. Okay? But I'm totally wrong. Okay? But then what
happens? Then he the the baby dies after. So if the only
problem with my taking possession was my subjective mindset it worked. My
error came to my benefit because I was certain I had a
right to it. I took it. It was a total דעת קנין.
da'at kinyan. The fetus wasn't קונה as a fetus and the fetus
was never born viable. So my קנין worked. But if it is
based on the fact not of my subjective of mindset, but that
the fetus actually does own it because the fetus can inherit, then
my taking of possession did not work. I thought the wife had
miscarried, but she hadn't. There was a fetus, the fetus had, you
know, and who has who was and that fetus inherited after his
father died. And then only afterwards did the property become הפקר hefker
when the fetus was miscarried. Okay? So Abaye's answer is completely about
my subjective
reality, and if subjectively I believe that I can take possession, then
it will totally work because the fetus did not own it. And
according to Abaye, it is based on the—no, a fetus can own
property, can inherit property, you just can't take possession of property for
a fetus.
So if I understand, let's say I go into your apartment, you
know, like I don't know if it's הפקר hefker or not, but
I'm willing to take the chance, right?
Right, might as well be the first one to grab it.
Right, then not if you're there, just whatever. So I don't know,
then
it turns out—no, what do you mean you don't know?
Nothing is—maybe you מפקיר mafkir it, maybe you weren't, I don't know,
like, you know, then it turns out if you were, I'm קונה
because in my mind I had in mind to—yeah,
I mean, you wouldn't be legally allowed into my apartment or whatever.
If you heard rumors, you heard rumors, hey, did you hear a
rumor that Dov was—you know, somebody—you know, somebody was מזכה mezakke because
זכה לאדם שלא בפניו zacha l'adam shelo b'fanav and you know,
it was a case of, you know, שתק ולבסוף צוח shataka u'vasof
tzavach like the גמרא before. Somebody was מזכה mezake to Dov like,
you know, this beautiful computer, but then he says, no, I don't
want it, it's הפקר hefker or whatever, you know, and so on.
So did you—oh, I didn't know that rumor, great, well I think
it's true, let's go and I'm going to go into this בית
מדרש, beis medrash, I'll take his laptop, and if it turns out
it's true, then I will have been the first one there. Sure,
that would work. Okay, you wouldn't be allowed to come into my
property and do it or whatever, but yeah, why not? If I
really was מפקיר mafkir it and there was rumors about it one
way or the other, you weren't certain, why wouldn't it work?
Yes, so thinking about who would take care of the wife, does
she get a כתובה kesubah and would she have a שעבוד sheibud
on the property?
Oh, that's a good point. Oh, no, because the property would not—would
be—oh, that's a really good question.
If it's
הפקר מפקיע
שעבוד—I
hefker mafkia
sheibud think you're right.
I think it's a good point. I
can't—logically I would say, it's a good question. Logically I can't see
why הפקר hefker would revoke her שעבוד sheibud on the property. So
if I transfer property to somebody and my kids don't inherit it,
the wife still has a lean on that property. I don't see
why if the גר ger dies and he's מפקיר mafkir the property,
the leans wouldn't survive the הפקר. hefker. But that's a good question.
But you'd have to assume in this case that
her כתובה kesubah was paid to her upon his death from some
other source.
You wouldn't have to assume that, it could be that she'll be
left holding an empty bag, which sometimes happens with these cases. But
then she would take this piece of—then she would have to be
paid, assuming that the שעבוד sheibud survived the moment of הפקר. hefker.
And
let's—can I just make this more simple? Let's say there's no לקוח
lakoach who comes and grabs it. He dies, the גר ger dies,
she's pregnant, she bears a son, the son dies after one day.
What happens to the property? She gets it?
No. Now the son is another person who's inherited property who has
no heirs, and then it becomes הפקר. hefker. Why doesn't
she
get it? Why should she?
Oh, because—oh, as the mother, as the biological mother. Oh, thank you.
Yeah, she would get it. That is correct. That is correct.
One day old, she gets it.
Yes, that's correct.
Okay, תא שמע, ta shema, come in here.
Okay. תינוק בן יום אחד
נוחל ומנחיל, tinok ben yom echad nochal u'manchil, a one-day-old infant can
inherit and can bequeath.
We're not talking about a גר ger anymore. בן יום
אחד אין עוברו לא. ben yom echad in ubaro lo. Only—so now
we're still trying to argue, we've shifted our focus, right? We've already
acknowledged that a fetus might be able to inherit, but it's not
relevant for our discussion about whether you can be מזכה לעובר, mezake
le'ubar whether you could actually actively transfer property. Nevertheless, this is what
we're focusing on now. Can a fetus inherit? So here a משנה
says—this is a famous משנה in נדה Niddah where it lists the
different ages of a child, of a young boy, of a young
girl, etc., and the given הלכה halachic statuses. And it
says, once an infant is one day old, right, then the person
who would G-d forbid kill the child would be חייב chayav and
for רציחה retzicha etc. etc. So it says, one of the consequences
of being born, one day old does not mean a full day,
being born, is that you can inherit, the infant can inherit and
bequeath. So בן יום אחד אין עוברו לא. ben yom echad in
ubaro lo. Only one day old, not a fetus. So look, we've
proved again that a fetus cannot inherit, and certainly מזכה לעובר mezake
le'ubar לא קנה. So the גמרא says, אמר רב ששת amar Rav
Sheshet no, Rav Sheshet explained, and again, remember, Rav Sheshet is the
one that says that a fetus not only can inherit, but you
can be מזכה לעובר. So why does this משנה say that only
once it's one day old? נוחל בנכסי האם להנחיל לאחין מן האב.
nochal b'nichsei ha'em l'hanchil l'achin min ha'av.
So the first thing we have to explain before we wonder about
one day old or a fetus is: who cares? Right, whether the,
here's this guy, okay,
here's all of his kids,
and here's his one day old little baby, okay? And we say
that once it's one day old, it inherits, and then if he
dies, he bequeaths it. Now, who is he going to bequeath it
to? If he dies, his father also died. Who would he bequeath
it to? Come on, people, the brothers, right? He doesn't have any
children at this stage, he's one day old. Okay, so he bequeaths
it to the brothers. So the first question we have to ask
is what relevance was it saying that he inherits and he bequeaths?
Let's say he didn't inherit and bequeath until he was, I don't
know, a year old. So what would have happened? The father's property
would have gone to the brothers, right? So here too, the father's
property, it's going to go through him to the brothers, right? What
is the sort of relevance of saying this? Okay, so רב ששת,
Rav Sheshet, understand the question? Either way, the brothers are going to
get it. רב ששת Rav Sheshet says the relevance is that
not that he's inheriting from his
father, but that he's inheriting from his mother. Okay, his mother
doesn't have a husband right now, the husband whatever, divorced, she's dead,
etc. This is her son, she dies, but these are sons of,
that's not his father.
No, it is his father. But, biological father?
No, it is a biological father. But maybe they're divorced, alright, maybe
they're divorced or he already died, okay, it doesn't matter, okay? These
are kids from a different wife. Okay, so the mother dies, okay,
and besides I said the father is dead or divorced so it
doesn't go to the father. The mother dies, so her property goes
to him. Now, and then he dies, so then it's going to
go to his brothers on the father's
side, his half-brothers. Okay, so if he would not yet inherit, then
if he wasn't around yet or whatever, he wouldn't inherit, okay? Let's
say he had to be 10 years old to inherit. What would
the הלכה halakhah be? She would die, it would go to her
family, her father, her brothers, or whatever. Because he's at the age
to inherit and to bequeath, first it goes to him and then
when he dies, it's not going to go back to her family,
it's going to go to his paternal brothers. Okay, so that's just
to explain the משנה, the consequence of saying נוחל ומנחיל, nokhel u'mankhil,
why it matters since either way it's going to the brothers. Okay,
so he says no, it really does matter. Now once that's true,
why are we, רב ששת Rav Sheshet is going to use this
to explain why we only said one day old. Because for רב
ששת Rav Sheshet the same should be true if she was pregnant,
right? If she was a fetus and she was pregnant, right, so
this baby here should be able to be נוחל ומנחיל, nokhel u'mankhil,
correct? Right? Should also inherit as a fetus, correct? That's what רב
ששת Rav Sheshet has been saying. But here's the reason. Since the
scenario is that his mother died, that's why we didn't want to
talk about him being a fetus because, right, if the scenario was
his father died, you could say his father died, he inherits in
his mother's womb, עובר הוא נוחל. ubar hu nokhel. But since רב
ששת Rav Sheshet said the scenario of the משנה is that his
mother died, well one minute, if his mother died, the only way
he can inherit from his mother if his mother died is if
he survives his mother's death. Okay, if he were a fetus, רב
ששת Rav Sheshet says that's why we didn't talk about a fetus
because a fetus would not survive his mother's natural death. So the
גמרא says like
this: what about that moment then, where would you define the moment
when a woman dies as her child is being born?
Right, so I'll talk about that in a minute, okay, but a
child is only considered born once the head crowns, okay? But if
he survives, right, I want to talk, I'll talk about that in
a minute, okay. So דוקא בן יום אחד, davka ben yom echad,
so that's why it said one day because really a fetus could
inherit, but since the scenario is that the mother died, אבל עובר
לא, aval ubar lo, it wouldn't work if we were talking about
a fetus. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? דהוא מיית ברישא.
d'hu mayis b'reisha. When a mother dies, the fetus dies first and
therefore it's true a fetus can be נוחל, nokhel, but in a
case where his mother died, we couldn't have a scenario of him
being נוחל nokhel because he would die before his mother. And what
would happen if he would die before his mother? Why don't we
say, well okay, but since he, maybe he should still inherit it
after his mother's death and pass it on to his brothers? No,
ואין הבן יורש את אמו בקבר להנחיל לאחין מן האב. v'ein haben
yoresh et imo b'kever l'hanchil l'achin min ha'av. You've
got to love these nice tight phrases, you've got to totally unpack
them. Okay, a son does not bequeath, does not inherit, so if
he first died, this was number one, the fetus died, and then
number two, the mother died, okay, we don't say that he, now
that he's already buried, as it were, he's in the grave, he
can't virtually inherit from his dead mother once he's in the grave
and say well had he been alive he would have inherited, he'll
inherit in the grave and then pass it on to his brother
on his father's side, לאחין מן האב, l'achin min ha'av, okay, which
basically it's a complicated way of saying what you would expect. expected.
If he's already dead when his mother dies, you look for other
heirs.
You don't say let's pass it through the dead
son to the son's heirs. Okay. He has to do two things
as a dead child: inherit and then bequeath. Right, and we don't
say, right, exactly. Okay. So because he died first and then the
mother died, it doesn't go through him. If the mother died after
he's dead, it goes to the mother's heirs. And that's why even
though a fetus can inherit, in the scenario that we're talking about
when the child will inherit and pass on to his paternal brothers,
we didn't want to talk about a fetus because then you would
never have that scenario. What if she died first, he was a
fetus, but the fetus died after the mother? No, the גמרא'ס Gemara's
asserting that doesn't happen. So I'm going to get to that in
a minute. Now the גמרא says, the מימרא דהוא מאי סברא, meimra
dehu mai savra, you're telling me he always dies first? והא הוי
עובדא, Veha havei uvda, we have a case where a woman died
and a pregnant woman ופרכס תלתא פרכוסי, ufirchas tlata pirchusei, and the
in the stomach you could see that the
fetus was quivering three times. Okay. אמר מר בר רב אשי, Amar
Mar bar Rav Ashi, מידי דהוה אזנב הלטאה. midi dehavah aznav halata'ah.
No, that's like the tail of a lizard when you cut the
tail of a lizard off, it just flops around and it's really
dead already. So the child is dead. He might have some nerves
starting to cause the thing to move. Now תוספות Tosafot points out
one minute, this is not true, and he points out from other
גמרות Gemaras that the fetus can survive, particularly תוספות Tosafot says if
the mother suffers a violent death.
Like if the mother is, let's say, murdered, right, or whatever, an
accident. Okay.
So if she's like in a slow process of dying, you would
say that the fetus dies first. But if it's some type of
a trauma or whatever, like she's you know an accident or a
murder immediate, so then the fetus can survive. So תוספות Tosafot, says
אי הכי נמי ee hachi nami but that's not the case we're
talking about, which sort of leaves open the question about then the
משנה is still then imprecise because it should have said you have
to be a one-day-old baby to survive, right? There are cases where
even a fetus can inherit. There are cases that the mother could
die first. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot? doesn't really have an answer to
that. Okay. But anyway, but in terms of your question, David, I
was wondering the same thing. Like what, the גמרא never dealt with
a case about a woman dying in childbirth? Right. So תוספות says
there's another scenario in which the baby will survive the mother's death,
and that would be that she was כבר נעקר הולד, kvar ne'ekar
havalad, which means even before the child's head has crowned, okay, if
the child is already seen as like in the process of being
born and already seen like somewhat detached from the mother. Exactly what
that moment is is not exactly clear. But it's almost birth? Right,
yeah exactly. So at that time, once he's no longer totally his
life is no longer like dependent on the mother, it's possible that
the mother will die and the child will survive. Because obviously they
must have had cases of mothers dying in childbirth. So he's no
longer a fetus then. So he's no longer a fetus. Right, he
might not yet be born yet, but he's no longer a fetus,
okay? So he's no longer totally dependent on the mother of you
know biologically dependent. But what תוספות means here he's talking about an
immediate death, yeah? והא דקאמרינן מיתה על ידי אדם. Veha deka'amrinan mita
al yedei adam. Right, exactly. דומיא דמיתה על ידי מלאך המות. Dumya
demita al yedei malach hamavet. Yeah, okay. So right, exactly. I mean,
it's true, it's even in the תורה, Torah, right? בצאת נפשה כי
מתה, Betzeit nafshah ki meitah, etc. All right, so anyway, so it's
still funny, because according to רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, we could have
definitely had scenarios where the fetus inherited and died after his mother.
But anyway, we move on. Okay, so now the גמרא says like
this: מר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה דרבא אמר. Mar bereih deRav Yosef
mishmeih deRava amar. Now, now that we're talking about what is the
relevance,
this is no longer exactly needed to answer the question about does
a fetus inherit or not. We're sort of now a little immediately
more interested in why do you have to tell me that only
once he's born, since regardless it's going to pass
on to the brothers, right? That was the question. So רב ששת
Rav Sheshet introduced the mother. No, because we have
to tell me he's born and he bequeaths so that it's
going to go from the mother to the paternal brothers. But if
it's not about the mother, if it's inheriting from the father, okay,
so then why do you have to tell me he inherits and
bequeaths? Whether he inherits and bequeaths or he was never around, it'll
go straight to the brothers are going to get it. So we
have another answer to that question. So מר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה
דרבא אמר לומר שממעט בחלק בכורה. Mar bereih deRav Yosef mishmeih deRava
amar lomar shemema'et bechelek bechorah. No, there is a difference. I was
waiting for somebody to think of to sort of think about this.
Okay, here's the difference. Okay, let's say there are five let's say
there are, I don't know, four units of property, okay, equal-sized units.
If there was only three brothers, the kid had never been born,
how much would each brother get? Well, the בכור bechor would get
two and each of these would get one, right? Yes? Now, let's
say, however, now he's born, and then the father dies. Okay, how
much does everybody get? Well, you have to divide four by five
now, okay, so basically what you'll have is, if we make now
we're going to have five and each one of these is four-fifths
of a unit. People see that? So these are each going to
get four-fifths, four-fifths, and four-fifths, okay. Everybody see see that? Right? Because
what you have to do is you have to meaning they're meaning
you have to divide, right? I mean we've turned four, maybe make
it look like that, we've turned four into into five things of
four-fifths each, right? So now, the חלק בכורה Chelek Bechorah used to
be a whole unit. Now it's four-fifths of a unit. Now he
dies, and this part is divided equally. Okay? Right. So this guy
into thirds, right? So the בכור Bechor got a smaller piece of
the בכורה Bechorah because you recognized him as a brother first and
then, you know, the double portion was left. So even though this
now gets equally distributed, so you could say the brothers repossess the
property, that's all very nice, but because he had been born first
and then the father died, so there were more brothers initially, the
חלק בכורה Chelek Bechorah was less than it would have been. All
right, so that's that's why it's relevant to say when is the
moment that he inherits. Because the moment that he's considered an heir
means that you have to divide the property into more units before
you distribute which means the בכור Bechor double portion is going to
be smaller. All right. So now the גמרא says like this. לומר
שממעט בחלק בכורה, Lomar shemima'et bechelek bechorah, ודווקא בן יום אחד, vedafka
ben yom echad, and that's only one day, אבל עובר לא, aval
ubar lo, if he's still a fetus, not. Not because a fetus
doesn't inherit, this also comes to the defense of רב ששת. Rav
Sheshet. A fetus might very well inherit, but if his mother if
he's not yet born, right, and if his mother here is pregnant
with it, okay, right? So in that case, even if he's going
to get his portion, it's not going to fact he's not going
to factor in to determine the the double portion of the בכור.
Bechor. I'll do I'll show you the math in a minute. Let's
just finish the sentence. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why is that? דילדו
לו אמר רחמנא. Deyaldu lo amar rachmana. It says ילדו לו בנים,
Yaldu lo banim, okay, and whatever etcetera, okay, so it means דאמר
מר, de'amar mar, it means that when you figure out how many
brothers there are to determine the size of the חלק chelek of
the בכור, Bechor, you look at the kids that are already born.
The unborn kids might be heirs, but you don't factor them in
when you're figuring out the חלק chelek of the בכור. Bechor. דאמר
מר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה דרבא, De'amar mar bereih deRav Yosef mishmeih
deRava, בן שנולד אחר מיתת אביו, ben shenolad achar mitat aviv, אינו
ממעט בחלק בכורה. eino mima'et bechelek bechorah. A child born after the
father dies, yes, he's an heir, he might have even gotten his
portion while he was a fetus, like רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, but
he does not allow he does not factor into the size of
the בכור Bechor portion. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? דילדו
לו אמר רחמנא והא ליתא. Deyaldu lo amar rachmana veha leita. You
only look at the number of kids that were already born. So
in this case, okay, in this type of a case, the father
died. The kid wasn't born yet. Okay, so the kid wasn't born
yet, you had these four big pieces. You know what we should
do? Let's make these smaller, okay. Anyway, you have four big pieces
of property. These are one of the five pieces are 80 percent,
right? Exactly, these are four-fifths sizes. These are full sizes. Okay. So.
So, the father died, okay. You said, all right, look, we know
mom is pregnant here, but and God willing, be a healthy child
etc. etc. But, okay, but right now the בכור Bechor says I
want to figure out the size of my double portion, okay? So
the size of my double portion is based on the number of
kids that are that are exist right now.
There are or sons, what? That are born right now.
That are born right now. Thank you. That are born right now.
So there are three kids that are already born, so if there
are three kids that are already born, that means we divide the
property into four, and my double portion is a full unit, correct?
Okay, so I'm going to take my full unit. That's definitely going
to be my because were we to divide it just among the
three of us, each one of you would get one and I
would get two. Right. So my בכור Bechor portion is one unit.
Great. Now now this little baby boy gets born, okay, or even
if before he's born, maybe an עובר is נוחל. nochel. Now we
have to figure out not my בכור Bechor unit, you know, let's
keep it as an עובר. We'll work with רב ששת. Rav Sheshet.
You have two boxes, right? No, no, no. The extra unit is
only one. Meaning he's not taking his base and his בכור. Bechor.
The בכור Bechor unit is based what if you divided the property
just among the three? Each of them would have one and he
would have two. So his בכור Bechor piece is one unit. And
now there's three units left. Now let's divide this amongst the heirs.
Who are the heirs? The heirs include the... Okay, so three divided
by four brothers
is that each
brother gets, no, so these won't be four-fifths now, whatever. Anyway, each
brother gets now three-quarters. Exactly. Okay.
So the fetus is זוכה zoche
regarding the ירושה but not regarding the בכורה. bechora. The בכור bechor
is in... No, but wait, yes, but wait, correct. But here's the
thing though, if anybody is
doing the math, we're
still not up to four, okay? Because three-quarters whatever, this is going
to be nine-quarter, it's not going to be the four. So the
actual so what you have to do is, is that you actually
just because the reality is, wait, wait, does that work? No, it
works. I'm sorry, I take it back. It works. I forgot him.
Okay fine, I forgot him.
Okay right, right, okay fine. Okay, it works, it works. Okay, so
that's how it works. Okay, so yes in terms of the base
we all get an equal amount and he even gets it as
a fetus. Okay, but we only determine the base to divide after
we figure out my חלק בכור chelek bechor which I take off
the top and I take based on the number of kids that
are alive right that are born right now. And by the way,
I would just like to say as a בכור bechor I like
this very much. Excellent. Okay. So, okay, בסורא מתנו הכי, Besura matnu
hachi, that's how they taught it in Sura. בפומבדיתא מתנו הכי. Bepumbedita
matnu hachi. Here's how they taught it in Pumbedita. A similar הלכה
halacha but a different one. אמר מר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה דרבא,
Amar Mar brei deRav Yosef mishmei deRava, בכור שנולד לאחר מיתת האביב
אינו נוטל פי שנים. bechor shenolad le'achar mitat ha'aviv eino notel pi
shnayim. Let's say the בכור bechor is born after the father dies.
He doesn't get a double portion. Now somebody should be asking an
obvious question. If the בכור bechor is born... you can understand a
בכור bechor is born after the father died, right? But then who
are the other brothers? Thank you. So either he's the בכור bechor
of a twin, okay? So after the father dies, the wife gives
birth to twins. Or the father has multiple wives and he dies
leaving behind a couple of pregnant wives. Okay, so you could have
a בכור bechor born after the father died with other brothers that
came after him. In that case, the בכור bechor does not get
the double portion. A בכור bechor only is entitled to the double
portion if the בכור bechor is born before the father dies. So
all of the questions of how big of a portion and does
he get a portion all goes by the kids that are already
born. Even if a fetus inherits, you don't factor that in in
terms of what you need for בכור bechor is the kids to
already be born. Okay, so אינו נוטל פי שנים. eino notel pi
shnayim. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? יכיר אמר רחמנא והלאה. Yakir amar
Rachmana vehala'ah. It says כי את הבכור בן השנואה יכיר, ki et
habechor ben hasnuah yakir, he should recognize, which means he has to
be in a position to be able to recognize, which means that
the בכור bechor has to already be born. Now of course the
רשב''ם Rashbam says it doesn't mean that if the father is in
מדינת הים medinat hayam and dies without ever seeing his kid, that
his kid doesn't get a double portion, okay? Or if the father
is senile and doesn't recognize anybody, it doesn't mean that. It just
means that the kid has to be able to be, let's say,
at least recognized by others. He has to be born. Exactly. Okay,
יכיר אמר רחמנא והלאה דהא דיכיר. Yakir amar Rachmana vehala'ah deha deyakir.
Okay, now והלכתא הלכתא ככל הני שמעתתא דאמר מר בריה דרב יוסף
משמיה דרבא. vehilcheta hilcheta kechol hanei shema'ateta de'amar Mar brei deRav Yosef
mishmei deRava. We rule like all of those things we said in
the name of Rava, meaning we ruled that for the בכור bechor
to get, factor, figure out the בכור's bechor's double portion, you only
look at the kids that are born, and whether, and for a
בכור bechor to get a double portion, he already has to be
born. Okay, now how about the הלכה, halacha, is מזכה לעובר קנה
or not? Meaning number one, is an עובר יורש, ubar yoresh, right,
is one question
and number two is does מזכה לעובר work? He is יורש yoresh
by these words of Rava. He is יורש. yoresh. I don't know
yet. Right, meaning the words they would sound like, they're not explicitly
saying it, but because they
have to make these points,
they sound like that we can accept that he would be יורש.
yoresh. We don't know yet, but maybe. Right, right. It's still not
even explicit about יורש yoresh but certainly implied. Okay, so the גמרא
says אמר רב יצחק אמר רב יוחנן המזכה לעובר לא קנה. Amar
Rav Yitzchak amar Rav Yochanan hamezake le'ubar lo kana. No, he doesn't
work. It at least מזכה doesn't work, okay? But if you take
a look at תוספות, I'm just going there because it's easier to
find than the רשב''ם. Rashbam. והלכתא דהמזכה לעובר לא קנה, vehilcheta dehamezake
le'ubar lo kana, פירש ריב''ם דבירושה דבא מאליה יכול להיות דהלכה כרבי
יוסי. peresh Rivam debiyerusha deba me'eleha yachol lihyot dehalacha keRabbi Yosi. Okay,
so maybe he will still inherit. You see that little תוספות? Okay,
we're not debating that. Maybe yes, maybe no, that the fetus will
inherit, but מזכה לעובר does not work. ואי תאמר משנתנו, Ve'i temar
mishnatenu, now what about our משנה, that the guy is gifting this
money to his unborn child? So הוה דעתיה דאדם קרובה אצל בנו.
hava da'ateh de'adam krova etzel beno. Now, since a person really wants
his son or daughter to take possession, it'll work. Now, again, we've
had cases like this before which I have to tell you, I
still for the life of me can't understand. It's real very nice
that you really, really, really want your son to take possession. You
know what? If you don't have the right mechanism, if he's not
yet considered to be a person, a legal person or whatever it
might be, I don't know how you can do it. And let's
say, you know, but so it seems to situate that... Part of
the problem of מזכה לעובר *mizakeh l'ubar* is not in whether the
fetus is considered to be exist or not, but in the fact
of subjectively I can't relate to the fetus or not. So, you
know, so therefore, if it is if it's my child, you know,
if you hear somebody's wife is pregnant, בשעה טובה *b'sha'ah tovah* etcetera.
You know, it's like but your child, you know, you're already seeing
that child as like, you know, as as you know more as
a child that fetus more as a child already. So it seems
to situate the problem of מזכה לעובר *mizakeh l'ubar* more in this
subjective you know what that does to your mindset of how sincere
are you to transfer something to an unborn child. So if it's
your child, maybe you're able to get over that subjective hump. You
know, that seems to be the point in the גמרא *Gemara*. But
as a general rule, to anybody else's unborn child it would not
work. Now one more line, אמר ליה שמואל לרב חננא בר בגדתאה
*Amar leh Shmuel l'Rav Chanana bar Bagta'a*, he said to רב חננא
*Rav Chanana* from Baghdad, that's what it means, פוק אייתי לי בי
עשרה *Puk aytei li bei asara*, go gather me ten people, I
want to make a public proclamation, דאימא לכו באפייכו *d'eima lacho b'apacho*
and therefore I will tell you in their presence, המזכה לעובר קנה
*hamizakeh l'ubar kana*. And maybe he wanted to tell it to him,
meaning as if he's פוסק *paskening* a practical case, not just a
theoretical discussion, I want to publicize that I disagree with his previous
discussion, that I think מזכה לעובר *mizakeh l'ubar* works. But you know
what? Tough luck. והלכתא המזכה לעובר לא קנה *V'hilchata hamizakeh l'ubar lo
kana*, it doesn't work. Okay, so that doesn't work, although we make
exceptions number one possibly for ירושה הבאה מאליה *yerusha haba'ah me'eleha*, and
number two for your own child. There apparently your subjective desire is
very effective. Okay. And I guess we will end here. All right.
So but the point is...